Guide to the Joseph Lovett Papers MSS.629
Fales Library and Special Collections
Joseph Lovett Papers
1979-2006
Fales Library and Special Collections
MSS.629
7 Linear Feet in 16 manuscript boxes
1 audiocassette
Joseph Lovett was a documentary film and television producer, writer, and director whose films focused on raising awareness on health and LGBTQ issues. As a producer at ABC's 20/20, he became known for developing some of the first televised investigations into the AIDS epidemic and the inaction of the U.S. government. Additionally, he was known for producing In a New Light, an AIDS awareness primetime special from the 1990s; directing and writing Cancer: Evolution to Revolution (2001) for HBO; and directing and writing the feature-length film Gay Sex in the 70s (2005). The Joseph Lovett Papers (1979-2006) consist of materials related to film and television productions that were created and collected by Lovett. Materials include transcripts, research materials, and graphics for various 20/20 segments, In a New Light, and Gay Sex in the 70s.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Joseph Lovett in May 2023. The accession number associated with this donation is 2023.040.
Arrangement
This collection has not been arranged by an archivist. The materials are arranged in the order in which they were received from the donor.
Biographical Note
Joseph Lovett was a documentary film and television producer, writer, and director whose films focused on raising awareness on health and LGBTQ issues. Lovett started his career as a freelance editor and assistant working on networks, features, and industrials. Around 1974, he started working as an editor and producer at CBS News Magazine. In 1977, he produced his first film for CBS, Parents of Gays. In 1979, Lovett became a producer at ABC's 20/20, where he developed some of the first televised investigations into the AIDS epidemic and the inaction of the U.S. government. Additionally, he produced stories on Mike Tyson, the Duvaliers, and airline safety, among other subjects. In 1989, Lovett founded Lovett Productions, Inc. (later, Lovett Stories + Strategies), where he produced, in partnership with the Centers for Disease Control and ABC, In a New Light. In a New Light was a five-year AIDS awareness primetime special televised in the 1990s. In 2001, Lovett won a Peabody Award for writing, producing, and directing HBO's Cancer: Evolution to Revolution. His first feature, Gay Sex in the 70s, premiered at the Tribeca Film Festival in 2005, and was broadcast on the Sundance Channel in 2007. Over the years, advocacy organizations have honored Lovett with numerous awards, such as the AIDS Leadership Award. Lovett died in July 2025.
Source cited:
Lovett Productions. "Joseph Lovett." Accessed July 26, 2023. https://lovettproductions.com/joseph-lovett/.
Miguel Salazar, "Joseph Lovett, TV Producer Who Shed an Early Light on AIDS, Dies at 80," New York Times. Accessed August 12, 2025. https://www.nytimes.com/2025/08/06/business/media/joe-lovett-dead.html
Audiovisual Access Policies and Procedures
Audiovisual materials have not been preserved and may not be available to researchers. Materials not yet digitized will need to have access copies made before they can be used. To request an access copy, or if you are unsure if an item has been digitized, please contact NYU Special Collections (special.collections@nyu.edu, 212-998-2596) with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
Scope and Contents
The Joseph Lovett Papers (dated 1979-2006) consist of materials related to film and television productions that were created and collected by Lovett. Materials include transcripts and research materials (articles, clippings, and reports) for 20/20 segments produced by Lovett; most of the segments covered AIDS, but there are additional segments on Mike Tyson, Teddy Pendergrass, and aviation. Additionally, there are transcripts, correspondence, reviews, and publicity materials for the educational outreach program on AIDS called In a New Light. Also included are notes, photographs, and graphics for Gay Sex in the 70s and The Accident, documentaries produced, directed, and written by Lovett. The collection documents media coverage of LGBTQ health issues, with particular focus on the AIDS epidemic, including activism, public perception, and institutional responses.
Appraisal
Financial materials from Lovett's company, Lovett Productions, were appraised out of the collection.
Documentary films--Production and direction; Television producers and directors.; AIDS (Disease) and mass media.; Health care for LGBTQ+ people
- In a New Light Transcripts, Talent Booking and Show Information, 1993 (Box 1)
- In a New Light II Show Information; Daily Correspondence; The Accident Stills; "Aircraft Maintenance" Transcript and Research Material, 1986-1994 (Box 2)
- In a New Light Talent Master and Final Script; Publications and Media Seminar on AIDS, 1985-1994 (Box 3)
- Sex in the 70s Graphics; Research Materials on Plasma, AIDS, and Hospital Care; "AIDS III" for 20/20 Outline and Notes, 1981-2004 (Box 4)
- AIDS Research Materials and Notes; Viewers' Responses to "AIDS" Segment on 20/20; "Armand Hammer" Segment for 20/20 Transcript and Research Materials, 1983-1988 (Box 5)
- Transcript for 20/20 Segments on Teddy Pendergrass and Rough Final Script and Research for Mike Tyson; Duvalier Research Related to Lawsuit, 1986-1988 (Box 6)
- Transcript for 20/20 Segment on the Duvaliers; List of AIDS Organizations, National and International; In a New Light Correspondence, Rundown, Audit, Cost Report, and Treatment, 1980-1996 (Box 7)
- In a New Light: Sex Unplugged Endorsements, Publicity Folder, and Report; In a New Light, 1993-1994, Publicity and Clippings; Publicity Folder for Joseph Lovett, 1980-1997 (Box 8)
- Reporter's Notebooks; In a New Light Reviews; Gay Sex in the 70s DVD Cover, Condoms, and Photo Archive; "History of Cancer" for HBO Graphics and Photographs; "AIDS II" for 20/20 Transcripts and Research, 1985-2006 (Box 9)
- Gay Sex in the 70s Photo Archive, 2006 (Box 10)
- Logs, Transcripts, and Research for 20/20 Segments on Ross Perot, Voodoo in Haiti, and AIDS, 1983-1986 (Box 11)
- Transcripts for 20/20 Segments on AIDS, AIDS Clinics, Hanafi, Survivors, and Mike Tyson, 1980-1988 (Box 12)
- Transcripts for 20/20 Segments on James Baldwin and "Ultralights", 1979-1983 (Box 13)
- Transcripts and Logs for 20/20 Segments on "Ultralights," "Food: Craig Claiborne," and AIDS, 1983-1985 (Box 14)
- Transcripts for 20/20 Segments on AIDS and AIDS Addicts, 1985-1987 (Box 15)
- Research on AIDS and Syphilis; March on Washington for Lesbian and Gay Rights, 1983-1988 (Box 16)
- Audiotape from 1988 (Possibly Part of 1988 Research File), 1988-03-13 (Box Shared Fales 045, Audiocassette 629.0001)